let's see an elegant semicircle proof of
the double angle formulas for S and
cosine in the XY plane imagine the
origin as a point labeled
O then imagine a point labeled a that's
exactly distance one from o the line
segment O A has a length of one so we
can use it to create a semicircle of
radius one let's label the opposite
point of the semicircle as B we can take
the radius and rotate to some point C on
the semicircle let's imagine that this
Arc AC subtains an angle of 2 * T we can
create a right triangle by dropping a
perpendicular from point C down to the
x-axis and labeling the intersection
Point D in the right triangle OD d c the
leg opposite to the angle 2T has a
length of sine of 2T and the leg
adjacent to the angle of 2T has a length
of cosine
2T now we draw another triangle
connecting the points a c and B like
this by ph's triangle theorem this is a
right angled triangle and the right
angle occurs at Point C now consider the
triangle B pictured here the angle B is
supplementary to the angle 2T and
therefore has a measurement of 180 minus
2T because two of the side lengths of
this triangle are radi of the circle
they both have a length one and that
means that this triangle is isoceles so
the other two angles in this triangle
must be equal equal and therefore they
must both be T so that the full angle
measurement of the triangle is
180° notice that the right triangle ACB
has a hypotenuse of length two since it
consists of two radi of the semicircle
the leg opposite to angle T in this
triangle therefore has a length 2 * the
S of T and the leg adjacent to the angle
T pictured has a length 2 * a cosine of
T now we have enough information to
prove our double angle identities this
yellow shaded triangle right here is a
right angled triangle with one angle T
and this red shaded triangle here is
also a right triangle with one angle T
so these two triangles have the same
angle measurements and that means that
they're similar right triangles using
similarity we know that the ratios of
the short leg to the hypotenuse in the
two triangles are equal from this we can
conclude that the S of 2T / 2 * the
cosine of T is equal to 2 * the S of T /
2 but now the twos cancel on the right
side and we can rearrange this equation
so that it reads s of 2T = 2 * the S of
T * the cosine of T we can also use
similarity to see that the ratios of the
long leg length to the hypotenuse are
equal in both the
triangles from this we see that 1 + the
cosine of 2T / 2 * the cosine of T must
equal 2 * the cosine of T divided Again
by the hypotenuse of the big triangle
which is 2 2 we can cancel the twos on
the right side again and clear
denominators to see that cosine of 2T =
2 * the cosine s of tus 1 the identity
on the left sin of 2T = 2 * the S of T *
the cosine of T is the double angle
identity for the sign function and the
identity on the right cosine of 2 T = 2
* cosine 2 of tus 1 is the double angle
identity for the cosine function
together these form the double angle
identities for S and cosine and we prove
them using a semicircle diagram this
proof is due to Roger B Nelson check the
description for more information about
this proof or for a link to another
proof of the same facts that uses the
law of signs and the law of cosines in a
triangle